A Guide to the Papers of Dorsye E. Russell
Virginia Commonwealth University, Tompkins-McCaw Library
Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library
Dorsye E. Russell Collection 1942 - 1987
Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library, Virginia Commonwealth University, Richmond, Va.
2001/Nov/16
.8 linear feet
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Donated to the Thomkins-McCaw Library
Biographical/Historical Information
Dorsye Russell was known as a pioneer in Virginia nursing. At a time when women were not expected to continue their education past a bachelor's degree, Russell earned her master's making her one of the most educated nurses in Virginia. Russell has the distinction of being the only woman to have been the president of three major nursing organizations within Virginia; The Virginia Nurses' Association, Virginia League for Nursing, and the Virginia Organization of Nurse Executives.
Russell was heavily involved with the Medical College of Virginia Foundation and the Nursing Division of the MCV Alumni Association. She was a teacher and administrator and her legacy is one of service to the institutions she served. She was an assistant professor in nursing at MCV as well as at Patrick Henry Community College where she established their nurse training curriculum. She was director of nursing at several Virginia hospitals including Mary Washington Hospital in Fredericksburg, Kings Daughter's Hospital in Staunton, and Lynchburg General Hospital in Lynchburg. She was appointed to the Governor's Committee on Nursing by Governor Mills Godwin in 1966. This Committee provided an accurate view of the challenges and needs of the nursing profession in Virginia at a time when it was most needed. From 1965 to 1975, Russell served on the State Board of Nursing.
Russell was also instrumental in establishing the Dorsye E. Russell Leadership Fund at MCV's School of Nursing in 1996. This endowment was envisioned to provide the needed funding for a course in professional organizational leadership and to make MCV a "flagship school" in Virginia. It is also intended to provide the skills needed for leadership within nursing associations.
Russell received many awards during her professional career, but the two most important were the Nancy Vance Award, the highest award given by the Virginia Nurses' Association in 1982, and just after her death, she was honored as one of the 50 pioneering nurses in Virginia. Though she never married and had no children, her legacy lives on in the organization she helped to build and the profession in which she worked. Russell is buried in Richmond's Hollywood cemetery. Her obituary can be found in the Fredericksburg Press Lance-Star.
Milestones:
03 Dec, 1919: Born in Richmond, Virginia.
1938- 1940: Attended College of William and Mary.
1943: Graduated, Medical College of Virginia. (BS, Nursing)
1945-1949: Faculty, Assistant Professor of Nursing, St. Phillip School of Nursing, Medical College of Virginia.
1951: Graduated, Columbia University. (MA. Nursing Administration)
1956- 1958: President of the Virginia League of Nursing.
1965- 1970: Served as a Member of the Virginia State Board of Nursing.
1966- 1970: President of the Virginia Nurses' Association.
1966-1969: Member of the Governor's Committee on Nursing (Virginia)
1970- 1971: Asst. Professor of Nursing at Patrick Henry Comm. College.
1970- 1975: Served as a Member of the Virginia State Board of Nursing.
1982: Awarded the Nancy Vance Award by the Virginia Nurses' Association.
1984: Awarded the Outstanding Nursing Alumni Award by the MCV Alumni Association.
05 Apr. 2000: Died in Fredericksburg, Virginia.
03 May 2000: Honored as a Virginia Pioneering Nurse by the Virginia Nurses' Association.
Scope and Content
This collection contains correspondence, meeting minutes, reports, essays and published materials dating from 1942 to 1987, with the bulk of material dated from 1968 - 1973. This material deals mainly with Russell's work with the Virginia Nursing Association in which she served as an officer and later President. Missing from the collection are things related to Russell's personal affairs.
Arrangement
Records are arranged in chronological order.
Contents List
- Virginia Nursing Association (VNA), Papers collected during the tenure of Mrs. Russell as President and Mrs. Evans when they worked as officers for the VNA. (Box-folder 1)
  - Bylaws and bylaw amendments. 1967 - 1975, This folder includes the bylaws and amendments to the bylaws proposed to the Committee on Program. (Box-folder 1.1)
  - Documentation of the Virginia Nurses' Association; Executive Committee of the Board of Directors. 1961-1971, This folder contains minutes and correspondence regarding the Executive Committee. (Box-folder 1.2)
  - Documentation of the Virginia Nurses' Association; Board of Directors. 1960-1964, This folder contains minutes and correspondence regarding the Board of Directors. (Box-folder 1.3)
  - Documentation of the Virginia Nurses' Association; Board of Directors. 1965-1971, This folder contains minutes and correspondence regarding the Board of Directors. (Box-folder 1.4)
  - Documentation of the Virginia Nurses' Association; Financial Reports. 1963-1974, This folder contains the Financial Reports including Cash on Deposit, General and Special Fund Receipts and Disbursements. (Box-folder 1.5)
  - Documentation of the Virginia Nurses' Association; Financial Committee. 1969-1974, This folder contains minutes of the Financial Committee, reimbursement policies, meeting summaries, and other correspondence dealing with the activities of the Committee. (Box-folder 1.6)
  - Documentation of the Virginia Nurses' Association; Financial Committee 1969-1974, This folder includes anticipated income and budgets for 1973, 1974 as well as a CPA financial examination dated Dec. 31, 1973. Also included is an assessment for property owned by the Association. (Box-folder 1.7)
  - Documentation of the Virginia Nurses' Association; Agnes D. Randolph Fund 1967-1971, This folder includes a scholarship review of the fund designed to assist nurses in Tuberculosis sanitariums. It was discontinued as the number of cases dropped. (Box-folder 1.8)
  - Documentation of the Virginia Nurses' Association; McLeod-Smith-Montgomery Fund. 1970-1973, This folder includes a scholarship review of the fund designed to provide financial assistance to nursing students. Also included are the minutes of the committee and a copy of House bill H. R. 910 which provides for scholarships for nursing education. (Box-folder 1.9)
  - Documentation of the Virginia Nurses' Association; Student Nurses' Association of Virginia 1969-1970, This folder includes correspondence, meeting minutes, certification information as well as drafts of Student Nursing Association bylaws. (Box-folder 1.10)
  - Documentation of the Virginia Nurses' Association; Committee of Convention Program. 1970-1971, This folder contains agendas, meeting notes, workshop plans and other correspondence regarding the 1970 Convention held at the Golden Triangle Motor Hotel, Norfolk, VA. (Box-folder 1.11)
  - Documentation of the Virginia Nurses' Association; Advisory Council, Nurses' Professional Registries, VNA-VLN Coordinating Committee, Committee on Long and Short Term Goals, Committee on Professional Nursing Practice, Committee on Membership and Public Relations. 1971-1973, This folder consists of documentation of several committees of the Virginia Nurses' Association. (Box-folder 1.12)
  - Documentation of the Virginia Nurses' Association; Districts Presidents Correspondence. 1966-1971, This folder contains minutes of quarterly meetings as well as letters to the District Presidents from the Executive Director or Executive Secretary. (Box-folder 1.13)
  - Documentation of the Virginia Nurses' Association; Committee on Legislation. 1969-1970, This folder contains minutes of the committee meetings as well as information concerning pending legislation wanted by the VNA. (Box-folder 1.14)
  - Documentation of the Virginia Nurses' Association; Committee on Economic and General Welfare. 1969-1970, This folder consists of minutes of the Committee of Economic and General Welfare. (Box-folder 1.15)
  - Documentation of the Virginia Nurses' Association; General documents sorted by type 1971-1973, 1987, This folder contains reports, letters, charts, and several organizational goals. (Box-folder 1.16)
  - Documentation of the Virginia Nurses' Association; Committee Members Lists 1966, 1969 (Box-folder 1.17)
  - Documentation of the Virginia Nurses' Association; Letters from other State Nursing Groups and Companies 1970-1971 (Box-folder 1.18)
  - Newsletters of the Virginia Nurses' Association 1950, 1970-1971 (Box-folder 1.19)
    - The Non's Psalm 1950, Article by Edward P. McCright (Box-folder 1.19)
    - Up Ante, Article by the American Hospital Association (Box-folder 1.19)
    - Nursing Today Sep. 1969, Editorial by Sadie Barton Snellings, in VNA News. (Box-folder 1.19)
    - VNA News May, 1970, Vol. 1, No. 6 (Box-folder 1.19)
    - VNA News Feb. 1971, Vol. 2, No. 3 (Box-folder 1.19)
    - VNA News Apr. 1971, Special Edition (Box-folder 1.19)
    - VNA Newsletter to District Presidents Apr. 1971 (Box-folder 1.19)
    - VNA Legislative Alert Apr. 1971 (Box-folder 1.19)
    - VNA News Aug. 1971, Vol. 3, No. 1 (Box-folder 1.19)
    - Bedside Nurse May 1971, Washington News (Box-folder 1.19)
  - Booklets of the Virginia Nurses' Association. 1965-1967, 1972, This folder contains dinner programs and Annual Joint Meeting programs from the Virginia Nurses' Association and the Student Nurses' Association of Virginia. (Box-folder 1.20)
- Personal papers of Luna Thomas Evans. (Box-folder 2)
  - Personal papers of Luna Thomas Evans., This folder contains letters regarding business with and membership paperwork for Evans in the VNA. (Box-folder 2.1)
  - Personal papers of Luna Thomas Evans., This folder contains letters and paperwork involving the Equal Rights Amendment. (Box-folder 2.2)
  - Correspondence related to her duties as an officer in the Virginia Nurses' Association., This folder contains letters from Thelma L. Bishop, Barbara T. Walker, Kenneth L. Rinker, Richard Cowling, and Beverly T. Boyd. (Box-folder 2.3)
- Clippings from various newspapers. Arranged by Date., Clippings on nursing and finances. (Box-folder 3)
- Papers and articles involving Practical Nursing. (Box-folder 4)
  - Articles from The American Journal of Nursing. 1942-1949, This folder contains articles concerning practical nursing and training. (Box-folder 4.1)
  - Articles and papers from several different publications. 1940-1950, This folder includes articles and papers on practical nursing and training. (Box-folder 4.2)
  - American Nursing Association's Practical Nursing education and training. 1946-1972, This folder includes training guidelines; course outlines all dealing with defining a curriculum for practical nursing. (Box-folder 4.3)
  - Practical nursing extras. 1949-1950, This folder contains a poster depicting many newspapers clippings regarding practical nursing as well as a list of articles on the subject as well. (Box-folder 4.4)
- The American Nurses' Association.(ANA), These papers were collected over the years during which Mrs. Russell and Mrs. Evans served as board members of the American Nurse's Association. (Box-folder 5)
  - Statements, Master Plans and Summaries. 1949-1950, 1972 (Box-folder 5.1)
  - American Nurses' Association Information. 1961, 1968, This folder contains paperwork and the information packet given to new members of the ANA (Box-folder 5.2)
- Leadership and Supervisory training guides and suggestions. (Box-folder 6)
  - Addresses and how-to guides for training, teaching leaders and supervisors how to be better managers of time and personnel. 1948-1955 (Box-folder 6.1)
  - Leadership guides and training worksheets. (Box-folder 6.2)
- Papers Presented at the Annual Nursing Lectureship, MCV School of Nursing. 1967-1969, This folder contains a booklet with the first two papers given at this annual event as well as a copy of the third. (Box-folder 7)
  - Issues in Nursing, Written by Jo Eleanor Elliot (Box-folder 7)
  - A Historian's View on the Future of Nursing, Written by Dr. Helen Nahm. (Box-folder 7)
  - Nursing Education- Nursing Service Where Do They Meet?, Written by Luther Christmas, PhD, RN. (Box-folder 7)
- Awards and Artifacts
  - Paperweight: green marble with a clock., Inscription: "Sustained Distinguished Membership. Sadie Health Cabaniss Society. VCU/MCV School of Nursing."
  - Paperweight: Acrylic., Inscription: "Sadie Heath Cabaniss Society. VCU/MCV School of Nursing."
  - Ceremonial Urn: Pewter., Inscription: "Cabaniss Society, 1995" and "VCU/MCV"
  - Metal bookmark: gold toned., Inscription: "Celebrating 50 Years of Service. MCV Foundation 1949-1999".
  - Miniature picture, Inscription, "MCVAA Board of Trustees. April 22, 1994."